<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-12-25T18:01:24+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">DataScience</title><subtitle>Welcome to my website. Here, I will regularly post about useful DataScience tools and guides. If you have any question / suggestion, you can contact me via my email.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Finding correlation between variables in a data set</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/correlation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finding correlation between variables in a data set" /><published>2018-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/correlation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/correlation">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: justify&quot;&gt;

Data analysis is the next step after data cleaning. It is also very important to analyze the data in order to understand the interactions between variables. The first step in this analysis is to find any correlations between variables (columns) of your data set.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finding-correlations&quot;&gt;Finding correlations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: justify&quot;&gt;

Understanding the interactions between variables is very important when you are working with your data. Indeed, using useless variables can be a waste of (computing) time and using two variables that are strongly correlated (hence explaining the same thing) can lead to wrong results. With the “corrplot” package, you can quickly view the correlations between variables with a graphic. Dark colors indicate a strong correlation between variables. In this example, which is about cars, you can see a strong (positive) correlation between the horsepower (hp) of a car, and the number of cylinder in the engine of a car (cyl).

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/correlation.png&quot; width=&quot;750&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: justify&quot;&gt;

This positive correlation means that horsepower, in a car, changes in the same direction as the number of cylinder in the engine of a car. Usually, if you have more cylinders in the engine, it will have more horsepower.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;redundant-variables&quot;&gt;Redundant variables&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: justify&quot;&gt;

It is also important to distinguish strongly correlated variables, and redundant variables. Those can be easily mistaken. If two variables are strongly correlated, it can be because they are in fact explaining literally the same thing. For example, if you are studying the surface of a square depending on the length of the sides and the length of the diagonals, those two variables are explaining exactly the same thing since the length of the sides and the length of the diagonals are related in a square ! Every data set is different but you have to be sure that there are no redundant variables for the next parts of the analysis.

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Introduction</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to clean a data set ?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/data-cleaning" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to clean a data set ?" /><published>2018-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/data-cleaning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/data-cleaning">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: justify&quot;&gt;

In this post, we focus on the data cleaning. It is very important that **the data is clean before beginning any computation** or visualization as it can produce absurd results or even produce errors.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-cleaning&quot;&gt;Data cleaning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: justify&quot;&gt;

Cleaning a data set can be quite easy if you know what you are looking for and what you are doing. Here I will explain the most useful and common tasks that have to be done in order to be sure that the data is clean.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-data-set-has-to-make-sense&quot;&gt;The data set has to make sense&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: justify&quot;&gt;

You can check that the data set makes sense to you i.e look at the lines at the top and the bottom of the set and look at every value there. This is specific to each data set. For example, if you have a data set giving you the time of the day and the temperature at that time, just be sure that the values are physically correct (check the minimum and maximum of a column). In R, you can use the function `head()` or `tail()` to print the lines at the top or at the bottom of the dataset.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/head.png&quot; width=&quot;350&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deal-with-missing--absurd-values&quot;&gt;Deal with missing / absurd values&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: justify&quot;&gt;

Before any computations, the data set has to be clean i.e all the rows with NA values or absurd values have to be dealt with, otherwise, the next steps of your project will most probably give weird results or even produce an error.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;missing-values&quot;&gt;Missing values&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: justify&quot;&gt;

If the value is simply missing, you can choose to remove the line with it. It is not wise if your data set is small or if you would rather not lose any information. Another option is to replace the missing value by the mean or the median value of the column containing it.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/navalue.png&quot; width=&quot;350&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;absurd-values&quot;&gt;Absurd values&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: justify&quot;&gt;

If the value is absurd, for example if the column contains the temperature of a town (in Celsius), every day, and you see that a day, the temperature is over 100 degrees, you can have some doubts. In this case, it's the same as previously. You can choose to remove the line containing this absurd value, or just replace it with the mean or median value of the column.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/outlier.png&quot; width=&quot;350&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: justify&quot;&gt;

To conclude with, you have to be sure that your data set is clean before doing any computation. If you follow these quick steps, you will be able to clean your data sets very quickly. You just have to remember that every data set is unique. Hence a different cleaning for each data set.

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Introduction</summary></entry></feed>